<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on BLAST Working Group</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Home on BLAST Working Group</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 10:24:45 +0900</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jhublast.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Spatial Statistics</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/research/spatialstatistics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 13:44:30 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/research/spatialstatistics/</guid><description>A central application of spatial statistics is using geographically sparsely sampled data to create spatially continuous maps for policy-making. For example, the figure shows how the PM10 data from a small number of monitoring stations in Europe (left) are used to predict the pollutant&amp;rsquo;s distribution across the region (middle) as well as the probability of it exceeding the regulatory threshold (right). Learn more about spatial statistics here.</description></item><item><title>Abhi Datta</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/people/abhi-datta/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 10:47:58 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/people/abhi-datta/</guid><description>Abhi develops statistical and machine learning methods for large spatial datasets as well as Bayesian models for multi-source epidemiological datasets.</description></item><item><title>Gary Rosner</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/people/gary-rosner/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 10:47:58 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/people/gary-rosner/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lu Zhang</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/people/lu-zhang/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 10:47:58 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/people/lu-zhang/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Scott Zeger</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/people/scott-zeger/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 10:47:58 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/people/scott-zeger/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Yanxun Xu</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/people/yanxun-xu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 10:47:58 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/people/yanxun-xu/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Bayesian Computation</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/research/mcmc/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 13:41:30 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/research/mcmc/</guid><description>Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) has been an essential tool for Bayesian statistics, empowering posterior inference for otherwise intractable probabilistic models. While alternatives have emerged, MCMC remains one of the most reliable and broadly applicable approaches to characterize complex posterior distributions common in modern biomedical/public health applications. We push computational limits of Bayesian inference in the era of Big Data through fundamental innovations in MCMC and other computational algorithms.
(Figure: the novel &amp;ldquo;zigzag&amp;rdquo; variant of Hamiltonian Monte Carlo enables statistical phylogenetics software BEAST to infer correlation among relations between gene mutations and biological traits of viruses.</description></item><item><title>Precision Medicine/Health Data Analytics</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/research/precisionmedicine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 13:41:30 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/research/precisionmedicine/</guid><description>For a specific disease and clinical question of interest, a single data source rarely provide a sufficient number of patients, longitudinal coverage, and breadth of information. Generating actionable clinical insights on how to treat individual patients necessitates integrating patient experiences across multiple data sources. Bayesian inference provides a natural framework to account for the hierarchical structure of such data as well as to incorporate our scientific understanding of the underlying clinical and biological processes.</description></item><item><title>Aki Nishimura</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/people/aki-nishimura/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 13:44:30 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/people/aki-nishimura/</guid><description>Aki uses Bayesian methods and statistical computing to tackle methodological challenges in healthcare analytics and large-scale biomedical applications.</description></item><item><title>nnSVG: scalable identification of spatially variable genes using nearest-neighbor Gaussian processes</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220420/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 10:24:45 +0900</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220420/</guid><description>Spatially-resolved transcriptomics enables the measurement of transcriptome-wide gene expression along with spatial coordinates of the measurements within tissue samples. Depending on the technological platform, this is achieved either by tagging messenger RNA (mRNA) molecules with spatial barcodes followed by sequencing, or through fluorescence imaging-based in-situ transcriptomics techniques where mRNA molecules are detected along with their spatial coordinates using sequential rounds of fluorescent barcoding. During computational analyses of spatially-resolved transcriptomics data, an important initial analysis step is to apply feature selection methods to identify a set of genes that vary in expression across the tissue sample of interest.</description></item><item><title>Better with Bayes: surface-based spatial Bayesian modeling in functional MRI</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220406/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 11:18:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220406/</guid><description>Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) is a non-invasive indirect measure of neural activity, which is commonly used to study the function, organization and connectivity of the brain. Given its high dimensionality and complex spatiotemporal structure, fMRI data is often analyzed in a “massive univariate” framework wherein a separate model is fit at every location (e.g. voxel or vertex) of the brain. This approach ignores spatial dependencies, leading to inefficient estimates and a lack of power to detect effects, particularly in individual subjects.</description></item><item><title>Bayes in the time of Big Data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201028/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:49:32 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201028/</guid><description>Big Bayes is the computationally intensive co-application of big data and large, expressive Bayesian models for the analysis of complex phenomena in scientific inference and statistical learning. Standing as an example, Bayesian multidimensional scaling (MDS) can help scientists learn viral trajectories through space and time, but its computational burden prevents its wider use. Crucial MDS model calculations scale quadratically in the number of observations. We mitigate this limitation through massive parallelization using multi-core central processing units, instruction-level vectorization and graphics processing units (GPUs).</description></item><item><title>A Case Study Competition among Methods for Analyzing Large Spatial Data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201104/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:47:57 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201104/</guid><description>The Gaussian process is an indispensable tool for spatial data analysts. The onset of the &amp;ldquo;big data&amp;rdquo; era, however, has lead to the traditional Gaussian process being computationally infeasible for modern spatial data. As such, various alternatives to the full Gaussian process that are more amenable to handling big spatial data have been proposed. These modern methods often exploit low rank structures and/or multi-core and multi-threaded computing environments to facilitate computation.</description></item><item><title>Getting started with Bayesian modeling in Stan</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201118/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:46:52 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201118/</guid><description>Stan is a probabilistic programming language, designed primarily for Bayesian inference. Its main algorithm is an adaptive Hamiltonian Monte Carlo sampler, supported by a state-of-the-art automatic differentiation library. Beyond model fitting, the Stan framework is designed to support a comprehensive modeling workflow. Using a simple example, I&amp;rsquo;ll demonstrate how to code and run a model in Stan; how to analyze samples from our posterior distribution using various diagnostics such as posterior predictive checks; and, based on these diagnoses, how to improve our model.</description></item><item><title>Spatial Factor Modeling: A Bayesian Matrix-Normal Approach for Misaligned Data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201202/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:45:11 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201202/</guid><description>Multivariate spatially-oriented data sets are prevalent in the environmental and physical sciences. Investigators aim to model multiple variables, each indexed by a spatial location, jointly to capture spatial association for each variable as well as associations among the variables. We prefer multivariate latent spatial processes to drive the inference and allow better predictive inference at arbitrary locations. High-dimensional multivariate spatial data, which is the theme of this work, refer to situations where the number of spatial locations or the number of spatially dependent variables is very large.</description></item><item><title>Personalized Dynamic Treatment Regimes in Continuous Time: A Bayesian Joint Model for Optimizing Clinical Decisions with Timing</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210203/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:44:21 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210203/</guid><description>Accurate models of clinical actions and their impacts on disease progression are critical for estimating personalized optimal dynamic treatment regimes (DTRs) in medical/health research, especially in managing chronic conditions. Traditional statistical methods for DTRs usually focus on estimating the optimal treatment or dosage at each given medical intervention, but overlook the important question of &amp;ldquo;when this intervention should happen.&amp;rdquo; We fill this gap by building a generative model for a sequence of medical interventions&amp;ndash;which are discrete events in continuous time&amp;ndash;with a marked temporal point process (MTPP) where the mark is the assigned treatment or dosage.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Hamiltonian Monte Carlo</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210217/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:43:02 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210217/</guid><description>Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC) is a state-of-the-art Markov chain Monte Carlo algorithm for Bayesian computation, forming a backbone of popular Bayesian inference software packages such as Stan and PyMC. Even though these packages automate posterior computation for users, basic understanding of HMC remains essential to obtain best computational performances out of these packages. For example, HMC &amp;mdash; and hence software based on it &amp;mdash; is highly sensitive to model parametrization. In this tutorial, I will explain inner workings of HMC and its implementations that are most relevant to its practical performances.</description></item><item><title>Two approaches to unmeasured spatial confounding</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210303/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:42:05 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210303/</guid><description>Spatial confounding has different interpretations in the spatial and causal inference literatures. I will begin this talk by clarifying these two interpretations. Then, seeing spatial confounding through the causal inference lense, I discuss two approaches to account for unmeasured variables that are spatially structured when we are interested in estimating causal effects. The first approach is based on the propensity score. We introduce the distance adjusted propensity scores (DAPS) that combine spatial distance and propensity score difference of treated and control units in a single quantity.</description></item><item><title>Modeling cell-free DNA fragmentation in human cancers</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210317/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:26:23 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210317/</guid><description>Cell-free DNA in the blood provides a non-invasive diagnostic avenue for patients with cancer. However, characteristics of the origins and molecular features of cell-free DNA are poorly understood. Here we developed an approach to evaluate fragmentation patterns of cell-free DNA across the genome, and found that profiles of healthy individuals reflected nucleosomal patterns of white blood cells, whereas patients with cancer had altered fragmentation profiles. We used this method to analyse the fragmentation profiles of 236 patients with breast, colorectal, lung, ovarian, pancreatic, gastric or bile duct cancer and 245 healthy individuals.</description></item><item><title>Disease Risk Modeling and Visualization using R-INLA</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210331/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:25:13 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210331/</guid><description>Disease risk models are essential to inform public health and policy. These models can be used to quantify disease burden, understand geographic and temporal patterns, identify risk factors, and measure inequalities. In this tutorial we will learn how to estimate disease risk and quantify risk factors using spatial data. We will also create interactive maps of disease risk and risk factors, and introduce presentation options such as interactive dashboards. The tutorial examples will focus on health applications, but the approaches covered are also applicable to other fields that use georeferenced data including ecology, demography or the environment.</description></item><item><title>Reversible Hamiltonian zigzag sampler outperforms its non-reversible competitors to learn correlation among mixed-type biological traits</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210428/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 17:58:33 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210428/</guid><description>Inferring correlation among multiple continuous and discrete biological traits along an evolutionary history remains an important yet challenging problem. We jointly model these mixed-type traits through data augmentation and a phylogenetic multivariate probit model. With large sample sizes, posterior computation under this model is problematic, as it requires repeated sampling from a high-dimensional truncated Gaussian distribution with strong correlation. For this task, we propose the Hamiltonian zigzag sampler based on Laplace momentum, one state-of-the-art Markov chain Monte Carlo method.</description></item><item><title>Generalized Additive Neutral to the Right Regression for Survival Analysis</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210512/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 17:53:47 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210512/</guid><description>We present a novel Bayesian nonparametric model for regression in survival analysis. The model builds on the neutral to the right model of Doksum (1974) and on the Cox proportional hazards model of Kim and Lee (2003). The use of a vector of dependent Bayesian nonparametric priors allows us to efficiently model the hazard as a function of covariates whilst allowing non-proportionality. Properties of the model and inference schemes will be discussed.</description></item><item><title>Latent Gaussian Model Boosting</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211013/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 14:19:12 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211013/</guid><description>Latent Gaussian models and boosting are widely used techniques in statistics and machine learning. Tree-boosting shows excellent predictive accuracy on many data sets, but potential drawbacks are that it assumes conditional independence of samples, produces discontinuous predictions for, e.g., spatial data, and it can have difficulty with high-cardinality categorical variables. Latent Gaussian models, such as Gaussian process and grouped random effects models, are flexible prior models that allow for making probabilistic predictions.</description></item><item><title>Variational Methods for Latent Variable Problems: Part I</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211027/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 14:18:30 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211027/</guid><description>Many practical problems in statistical inference involve &amp;ldquo;latent&amp;rdquo; variables, by which I will mean high-dimensional, unobserved nuisance parameters or missing data which must be accounted for when performing inference on some lower-dimensional quantity of primary interest. Common examples include random effects models (the random effects are the latent variables) and mixture models (where the component indicators are the latent variables). I will introduce and discuss variational inference (VI) methods for latent variable problems, drawing connections both with Bayesian approaches (Markov Chain Monte Carlo and the maximum a-posteriori estimator) and frequentist approaches (maximum likelihood estimators and the EM algorithm).</description></item><item><title>Variational Methods for Latent Variable Problems: Part II</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211110/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 14:17:34 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211110/</guid><description>Many practical problems in statistical inference involve &amp;ldquo;latent&amp;rdquo; variables, by which I will mean high-dimensional, unobserved nuisance parameters or missing data which must be accounted for when performing inference on some lower-dimensional quantity of primary interest. Common examples include random effects models (the random effects are the latent variables) and mixture models (where the component indicators are the latent variables). I will introduce and discuss variational inference (VI) methods for latent variable problems, drawing connections both with Bayesian approaches (Markov Chain Monte Carlo and the maximum a-posteriori estimator) and frequentist approaches (maximum likelihood estimators and the EM algorithm).</description></item><item><title>Variational Methods for Latent Variable Problems: Part III</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211117/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 23:52:36 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211117/</guid><description>Many practical problems in statistical inference involve &amp;ldquo;latent&amp;rdquo; variables, by which I will mean high-dimensional, unobserved nuisance parameters or missing data which must be accounted for when performing inference on some lower-dimensional quantity of primary interest. Common examples include random effects models (the random effects are the latent variables) and mixture models (where the component indicators are the latent variables). I will introduce and discuss variational inference (VI) methods for latent variable problems, drawing connections both with Bayesian approaches (Markov Chain Monte Carlo and the maximum a-posteriori estimator) and frequentist approaches (maximum likelihood estimators and the EM algorithm).</description></item><item><title>Spatial meshing for general Bayesian multivariate models</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220309/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 14:58:24 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220309/</guid><description>Quantifying spatial associations in multivariate geolocated data of different types is achievable via random effects in a Bayesian hierarchical model, but severe computational bottlenecks arise when spatial dependence is encoded as a latent Gaussian process (GP) in the increasingly common large scale data settings on which we focus. The scenario worsens in non-Gaussian models because the reduced analytical tractability leads to additional hurdles to computational efficiency. We introduce methodologies for efficiently computing multivariate Bayesian models of spatially referenced non-Gaussian data.</description></item><item><title>Recent Experiences Conducting Trials using Bayesian Response Adaptive Randomization</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220223/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 14:57:14 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220223/</guid><description>I will discuss my experiences coordinating two recent clinical trials in out-of-hospital cardiac arrest that used Bayesian response adaptive randomization designs, and present some methodological innovations to improve implementation and understand the potential benefit these designs offer. I will discuss the ACCESS trial (Clinicaltrials.gov ID: NCT03119571), which sought to compare the efficacy of two standards or care: direct admission to the cardiac catheter laboratory versus the ICU; and the ARREST trial (NCT03880565), which sought to evaluate the efficacy of in-transit ECMO-facilitated resuscitation versus standard Advanced Cardiac Life Support (ACLS) resuscitation.</description></item><item><title>A Bayesian predictive platform design for proof of concept and dose finding using early and late endpoints</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220209/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 14:55:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220209/</guid><description>Evaluating long-term benefits of potential new treatments for chronic diseases can be very time-consuming and costly. We propose a Bayesian predictive platform design that provides a unified framework for evaluating multiple investigational agents in a multistage, randomized controlled trial. The design expedites the drug evaluation process and reduces development costs by including dose finding, futility and superiority monitoring, and enrichment, while avoiding over-allocating patients to a shared placebo or active control arm.</description></item></channel></rss>