<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Events on BLAST Working Group</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/</link><description>Recent content in Events on BLAST Working Group</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 10:04:39 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jhublast.github.io/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bayesian extension of Multilevel Functional Principal Components Analysis with application to Continuous Glucose Monitoring Data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20240501/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 10:04:39 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20240501/</guid><description>Multilevel functional principal components analysis (MFPCA) facilitates estimation of hierarchical covariance structures for functional data produced by wearable sensors, including continuous glucose monitors (CGM), all while accounting for covariate effects. There are several existing methods to efficiently fit these types of models, including the eminent fast covariance estimation and the recently proposed procedure of fitting appropriate localized mixed effects models and smoothing (Xiao et al. 2016, Leroux et al. 2023). However, these methods do not inherently account for uncertainty in the eigenfunctions during the estimation procedure.</description></item><item><title>Estimation and false discovery control for the analysis of environmental mixtures</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20231115/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 13:31:46 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20231115/</guid><description>The analysis of environmental mixtures is of growing importance in environmental epidemiology, and one of the key goals in such analyses is to identify exposures and their interactions that are associated with adverse health outcomes. Typical approaches utilize flexible regression models combined with variable selection to identify important exposures and estimate a potentially nonlinear relationship with the outcome of interest. Despite this surge in interest, no approaches to date can identify exposures and interactions while controlling any form of error rates with respect to exposure selection.</description></item><item><title>The Modified Ziggurat Algorithm for Skewed Shrinkage Prior</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20231018/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 11:49:46 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20231018/</guid><description>Consortiums of health databases utilize standardized vocabularies to facilitate multi-institutional studies based upon their constituent data. However, synthesizing this heterogeneous clinical data is hampered by variation between ostensibly unified terminologies, with each constituent dataset providing a different set of clinical covariates. Notably, we observe ontological relationships among these covariates, and those related covariates likely contribute similarly to treatment decisions and health outcomes. Here, we extend the Bayesian hierarchical model framework by encoding ontological relations among covariates in the form of correlations in corresponding parameters.</description></item><item><title>BLAST trainee presentations</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20231003/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 15:48:22 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20231003/</guid><description>A series of talks given by current PhD students and postdocs in the BLAST group.</description></item><item><title>Spatial predictions on physically constrained domains: Applications to Arctic sea salinity data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230927/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 14:23:08 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230927/</guid><description>In this paper, we predict sea surface salinity (SSS) in the Arctic Ocean based on satellite measurements. SSS is a crucial indicator for ongoing changes in the Arctic Ocean and can offer important insights about climate change. We particularly focus on areas of water mistakenly flagged as ice by satellite algorithms. To remove bias in the retrieval of salinity near sea ice, the algorithms use conservative ice masks, which result in considerable loss of data.</description></item><item><title>Proximal MCMC for Bayesian Inference of Constrained and Regularized Estimation</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230517/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 18:56:10 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230517/</guid><description>This paper advocates proximal Markov Chain Monte Carlo (ProxMCMC) as a flexible and general Bayesian inference framework for constrained or regularized estimation. Originally introduced in the Bayesian imaging literature, ProxMCMC employs the Moreau-Yosida envelope for a smooth approximation of the total-variation regularization term, fixes nuisance and regularization parameters as constants, and relies on the Langevin algorithm for the posterior sampling. We extend ProxMCMC to the full Bayesian framework with modeling and data-adaptive estimation of all parameters including the regularization strength parameter.</description></item><item><title>A dynamic spatial filtering approach to mitigate underestimation bias in field calibrated low-cost sensor air pollution data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230405-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 09:45:13 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230405-2/</guid><description>Low-cost air pollution sensors, offering hyper-local characterization of pollutant concentrations, are becoming increasingly prevalent in environmental and public health research. However, low-cost air pollution data can be noisy, biased by environmental conditions, and usually need to be field-calibrated by collocating low-cost sensors with reference-grade instruments. We show that the common procedure of regression-based calibration using collocated data systematically underestimates high air pollution concentrations, which are critical to diagnose from a health perspective.</description></item><item><title>Polygenic Risk Predication via Bayesian Bridge Prior</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230405/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 09:45:01 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230405/</guid><description>Polygenic Risk Scores (PRS) have shown great promise in predicting the genetic variation in complex human traits and diseases. Although a series of methods have been proposed to construct PRS, their relative performance varies a lot by not only the genetic architectures of the traits/diseases, but also the training GWAS sample size and LD reference panel. There is still a strong need for novel methods that have more flexible assumptions for effect size distribution and are less sensitive to the sample size of LD reference panel.</description></item><item><title>Scalable Bayesian inference using non-reversible parallel tempering</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230308/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 16:31:21 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230308/</guid><description>Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods are the most widely used tools in Bayesian statistics for making inferences from complex posterior distributions. MCMC works by constructing a Markov chain stationary with respect to the posterior and averaging the statistics over its trajectory. In practice, for challenging problems where the posterior is high-dimensional with well-separated modes, MCMC algorithms can get trapped exploring local regions of high probability and fail to converge reliably in a finite time.</description></item><item><title>JHU Infectious Disease Dynamics Modeling Group</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230222/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 15:21:17 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230222/</guid><description>An overview of the Infectious Disease Dynamics (IDD) modeling group&amp;rsquo;s research portfolio, with short talks highlighting ongoing work and discussion of possible collaborations. The IDD is made up of faculty, post-docs, graduate and undergraduate students who are interested in the dynamics of a wide span of infectious diseases, from dengue to influenza to chikungunya, based at the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health. The group uses a combination of theoretical and empirical approaches to study transmission dynamics.</description></item><item><title>Hamiltonianizing a piecewise deterministic Markov process: a bouncy particle sampler with "inertia"</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230208/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 11:22:24 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20230208/</guid><description>The Bouncy Particle Sampler is among the most prominent examples of piecewise deterministic Markov process samplers, a state-of-the-art paradigm in Bayesian computation. Inspired by recent connections to the Hamiltonian Monte Carlo paradigm, we present a Monte Carlo algorithm intimately related to the Bouncy Particle Sampler but relying on Hamiltonian-like dynamics which generate a piecewise linear trajectory similar to the Bouncy Particle Sampler&amp;rsquo;s. However, changes in its velocity occur deterministically in the manner of Hamiltonian dynamics, dictated by the auxiliary &amp;ldquo;inertia&amp;rdquo; parameter we introduce.</description></item><item><title>Spectral approaches to speed up Bayesian inference for large stationary time series data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221207/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 17:53:50 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221207/</guid><description>This talk will discuss some recent approaches to speed up MCMC for large stationary time series data via data subsampling. We discuss the Whittle log-likelihood for univariate time series and some properties that allow estimating the log-likelihood via data subsampling. We also consider an extension to multivariate time series via the multivariate Whittle log-likelihood and propose a novel model that parsimoniously models semi-long memory properties of multivariate time series.</description></item><item><title>Learning and Predicting from Dynamic Models for COVID-19 Patient Monitoring</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221109-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 11:28:56 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221109-2/</guid><description>COVID-19 has challenged health systems to learn how to learn. This talk describes the context and methods for learning from EHR data at one academic health center. We use Bayesian hierarchical regression to jointly model 1) major survival outcomes including discharge, ventilation, and death, and 2) multivariate biomarker processes that describe a patient’s disease trajectory. We focus on dynamic models using Bayesian machinery in which both the predictors and survival outcomes vary over time.</description></item><item><title>Bayesian penalized monotoneregression for quantifying Alzheimer disease progression with biomarkers</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221109/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 11:25:48 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221109/</guid><description>Several biomarkers are hypothesized to indicate early stagesof Alzheimer’s disease, well before the cognitive symptoms manifest. Theirprecise relations to the disease progression, however, is poorly understood.This limits our ability to diagnose the disease and intervene at early stages.To better quantify how the disease and biomarkers progress, we propose a jointmodel in which biomarkers are modeled as increasing functions of a latentdisease progression parameter. In estimating these functions, we deploymonotone regression splines with smoothness penalty to flexibly model increasingfunctions.</description></item><item><title>A Second Look at Spatial Confounding in Spatial Linear Mixed Models</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221025/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 16:39:47 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221025/</guid><description>In the last two decades, considerable research has been devoted to a phenomenon known as spatial confounding. Spatial confounding is thought to occur when there is collinearity between a covariate and the random effect in a spatial regression model. This collinearity is often considered highly problematic when the inferential goal is estimating regression coefficients, and various methodologies have been proposed to &amp;ldquo;alleviate&amp;rdquo; it. Recently, it has become apparent that many of these methodologies are flawed, yet the field continues to expand.</description></item><item><title>Efficient Alternatives for Bayesian Hypothesis Tests in Psychology</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 11:16:38 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20221012/</guid><description>Bayesian hypothesis testing procedures have gained increased acceptance in recent years. A key advantage of Bayesian tests over classical testing procedures is their potential to quantify information supporting true null hypotheses. Ironically, default implementations of Bayesian tests prevent the accumulation of strong evidence in favor of true null hypotheses because associated default alternative hypotheses assign a high probability to data that are most consistent with a null effect. We propose the use of &amp;ldquo;non-local&amp;rdquo; alternative hypotheses to resolve this paradox.</description></item><item><title>Bypassing Markov Chains for Bayesian Generalized Linear Mixed Effects Models</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220504/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 10:38:21 +0900</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220504/</guid><description>Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) is an all-purpose tool that allows one to generate dependent replicates from a posterior distribution for effectively any Bayesian hierarchical model. As such, MCMC has become a standard in Bayesian statistics. However, convergence issues, tuning, and the effective sample size of the MCMC are nontrivial considerations that are often overlooked or can be difficult to assess. Moreover, these practical issues can produce a significant computational burden.</description></item><item><title>nnSVG: scalable identification of spatially variable genes using nearest-neighbor Gaussian processes</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220420/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 10:24:45 +0900</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220420/</guid><description>Spatially-resolved transcriptomics enables the measurement of transcriptome-wide gene expression along with spatial coordinates of the measurements within tissue samples. Depending on the technological platform, this is achieved either by tagging messenger RNA (mRNA) molecules with spatial barcodes followed by sequencing, or through fluorescence imaging-based in-situ transcriptomics techniques where mRNA molecules are detected along with their spatial coordinates using sequential rounds of fluorescent barcoding. During computational analyses of spatially-resolved transcriptomics data, an important initial analysis step is to apply feature selection methods to identify a set of genes that vary in expression across the tissue sample of interest.</description></item><item><title>Better with Bayes: surface-based spatial Bayesian modeling in functional MRI</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220406/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 11:18:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220406/</guid><description>Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) is a non-invasive indirect measure of neural activity, which is commonly used to study the function, organization and connectivity of the brain. Given its high dimensionality and complex spatiotemporal structure, fMRI data is often analyzed in a “massive univariate” framework wherein a separate model is fit at every location (e.g. voxel or vertex) of the brain. This approach ignores spatial dependencies, leading to inefficient estimates and a lack of power to detect effects, particularly in individual subjects.</description></item><item><title>Bayes in the time of Big Data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201028/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:49:32 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201028/</guid><description>Big Bayes is the computationally intensive co-application of big data and large, expressive Bayesian models for the analysis of complex phenomena in scientific inference and statistical learning. Standing as an example, Bayesian multidimensional scaling (MDS) can help scientists learn viral trajectories through space and time, but its computational burden prevents its wider use. Crucial MDS model calculations scale quadratically in the number of observations. We mitigate this limitation through massive parallelization using multi-core central processing units, instruction-level vectorization and graphics processing units (GPUs).</description></item><item><title>A Case Study Competition among Methods for Analyzing Large Spatial Data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201104/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:47:57 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201104/</guid><description>The Gaussian process is an indispensable tool for spatial data analysts. The onset of the &amp;ldquo;big data&amp;rdquo; era, however, has lead to the traditional Gaussian process being computationally infeasible for modern spatial data. As such, various alternatives to the full Gaussian process that are more amenable to handling big spatial data have been proposed. These modern methods often exploit low rank structures and/or multi-core and multi-threaded computing environments to facilitate computation.</description></item><item><title>Getting started with Bayesian modeling in Stan</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201118/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:46:52 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201118/</guid><description>Stan is a probabilistic programming language, designed primarily for Bayesian inference. Its main algorithm is an adaptive Hamiltonian Monte Carlo sampler, supported by a state-of-the-art automatic differentiation library. Beyond model fitting, the Stan framework is designed to support a comprehensive modeling workflow. Using a simple example, I&amp;rsquo;ll demonstrate how to code and run a model in Stan; how to analyze samples from our posterior distribution using various diagnostics such as posterior predictive checks; and, based on these diagnoses, how to improve our model.</description></item><item><title>Spatial Factor Modeling: A Bayesian Matrix-Normal Approach for Misaligned Data</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201202/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:45:11 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20201202/</guid><description>Multivariate spatially-oriented data sets are prevalent in the environmental and physical sciences. Investigators aim to model multiple variables, each indexed by a spatial location, jointly to capture spatial association for each variable as well as associations among the variables. We prefer multivariate latent spatial processes to drive the inference and allow better predictive inference at arbitrary locations. High-dimensional multivariate spatial data, which is the theme of this work, refer to situations where the number of spatial locations or the number of spatially dependent variables is very large.</description></item><item><title>Personalized Dynamic Treatment Regimes in Continuous Time: A Bayesian Joint Model for Optimizing Clinical Decisions with Timing</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210203/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:44:21 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210203/</guid><description>Accurate models of clinical actions and their impacts on disease progression are critical for estimating personalized optimal dynamic treatment regimes (DTRs) in medical/health research, especially in managing chronic conditions. Traditional statistical methods for DTRs usually focus on estimating the optimal treatment or dosage at each given medical intervention, but overlook the important question of &amp;ldquo;when this intervention should happen.&amp;rdquo; We fill this gap by building a generative model for a sequence of medical interventions&amp;ndash;which are discrete events in continuous time&amp;ndash;with a marked temporal point process (MTPP) where the mark is the assigned treatment or dosage.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Hamiltonian Monte Carlo</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210217/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:43:02 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210217/</guid><description>Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC) is a state-of-the-art Markov chain Monte Carlo algorithm for Bayesian computation, forming a backbone of popular Bayesian inference software packages such as Stan and PyMC. Even though these packages automate posterior computation for users, basic understanding of HMC remains essential to obtain best computational performances out of these packages. For example, HMC &amp;mdash; and hence software based on it &amp;mdash; is highly sensitive to model parametrization. In this tutorial, I will explain inner workings of HMC and its implementations that are most relevant to its practical performances.</description></item><item><title>Two approaches to unmeasured spatial confounding</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210303/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:42:05 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210303/</guid><description>Spatial confounding has different interpretations in the spatial and causal inference literatures. I will begin this talk by clarifying these two interpretations. Then, seeing spatial confounding through the causal inference lense, I discuss two approaches to account for unmeasured variables that are spatially structured when we are interested in estimating causal effects. The first approach is based on the propensity score. We introduce the distance adjusted propensity scores (DAPS) that combine spatial distance and propensity score difference of treated and control units in a single quantity.</description></item><item><title>Modeling cell-free DNA fragmentation in human cancers</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210317/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:26:23 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210317/</guid><description>Cell-free DNA in the blood provides a non-invasive diagnostic avenue for patients with cancer. However, characteristics of the origins and molecular features of cell-free DNA are poorly understood. Here we developed an approach to evaluate fragmentation patterns of cell-free DNA across the genome, and found that profiles of healthy individuals reflected nucleosomal patterns of white blood cells, whereas patients with cancer had altered fragmentation profiles. We used this method to analyse the fragmentation profiles of 236 patients with breast, colorectal, lung, ovarian, pancreatic, gastric or bile duct cancer and 245 healthy individuals.</description></item><item><title>Disease Risk Modeling and Visualization using R-INLA</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210331/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 18:25:13 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210331/</guid><description>Disease risk models are essential to inform public health and policy. These models can be used to quantify disease burden, understand geographic and temporal patterns, identify risk factors, and measure inequalities. In this tutorial we will learn how to estimate disease risk and quantify risk factors using spatial data. We will also create interactive maps of disease risk and risk factors, and introduce presentation options such as interactive dashboards. The tutorial examples will focus on health applications, but the approaches covered are also applicable to other fields that use georeferenced data including ecology, demography or the environment.</description></item><item><title>Reversible Hamiltonian zigzag sampler outperforms its non-reversible competitors to learn correlation among mixed-type biological traits</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210428/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 17:58:33 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210428/</guid><description>Inferring correlation among multiple continuous and discrete biological traits along an evolutionary history remains an important yet challenging problem. We jointly model these mixed-type traits through data augmentation and a phylogenetic multivariate probit model. With large sample sizes, posterior computation under this model is problematic, as it requires repeated sampling from a high-dimensional truncated Gaussian distribution with strong correlation. For this task, we propose the Hamiltonian zigzag sampler based on Laplace momentum, one state-of-the-art Markov chain Monte Carlo method.</description></item><item><title>Generalized Additive Neutral to the Right Regression for Survival Analysis</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210512/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 17:53:47 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20210512/</guid><description>We present a novel Bayesian nonparametric model for regression in survival analysis. The model builds on the neutral to the right model of Doksum (1974) and on the Cox proportional hazards model of Kim and Lee (2003). The use of a vector of dependent Bayesian nonparametric priors allows us to efficiently model the hazard as a function of covariates whilst allowing non-proportionality. Properties of the model and inference schemes will be discussed.</description></item><item><title>Latent Gaussian Model Boosting</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211013/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 14:19:12 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211013/</guid><description>Latent Gaussian models and boosting are widely used techniques in statistics and machine learning. Tree-boosting shows excellent predictive accuracy on many data sets, but potential drawbacks are that it assumes conditional independence of samples, produces discontinuous predictions for, e.g., spatial data, and it can have difficulty with high-cardinality categorical variables. Latent Gaussian models, such as Gaussian process and grouped random effects models, are flexible prior models that allow for making probabilistic predictions.</description></item><item><title>Variational Methods for Latent Variable Problems: Part I</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211027/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 14:18:30 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211027/</guid><description>Many practical problems in statistical inference involve &amp;ldquo;latent&amp;rdquo; variables, by which I will mean high-dimensional, unobserved nuisance parameters or missing data which must be accounted for when performing inference on some lower-dimensional quantity of primary interest. Common examples include random effects models (the random effects are the latent variables) and mixture models (where the component indicators are the latent variables). I will introduce and discuss variational inference (VI) methods for latent variable problems, drawing connections both with Bayesian approaches (Markov Chain Monte Carlo and the maximum a-posteriori estimator) and frequentist approaches (maximum likelihood estimators and the EM algorithm).</description></item><item><title>Variational Methods for Latent Variable Problems: Part II</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211110/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 14:17:34 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211110/</guid><description>Many practical problems in statistical inference involve &amp;ldquo;latent&amp;rdquo; variables, by which I will mean high-dimensional, unobserved nuisance parameters or missing data which must be accounted for when performing inference on some lower-dimensional quantity of primary interest. Common examples include random effects models (the random effects are the latent variables) and mixture models (where the component indicators are the latent variables). I will introduce and discuss variational inference (VI) methods for latent variable problems, drawing connections both with Bayesian approaches (Markov Chain Monte Carlo and the maximum a-posteriori estimator) and frequentist approaches (maximum likelihood estimators and the EM algorithm).</description></item><item><title>Variational Methods for Latent Variable Problems: Part III</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211117/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 23:52:36 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20211117/</guid><description>Many practical problems in statistical inference involve &amp;ldquo;latent&amp;rdquo; variables, by which I will mean high-dimensional, unobserved nuisance parameters or missing data which must be accounted for when performing inference on some lower-dimensional quantity of primary interest. Common examples include random effects models (the random effects are the latent variables) and mixture models (where the component indicators are the latent variables). I will introduce and discuss variational inference (VI) methods for latent variable problems, drawing connections both with Bayesian approaches (Markov Chain Monte Carlo and the maximum a-posteriori estimator) and frequentist approaches (maximum likelihood estimators and the EM algorithm).</description></item><item><title>Spatial meshing for general Bayesian multivariate models</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220309/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 14:58:24 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220309/</guid><description>Quantifying spatial associations in multivariate geolocated data of different types is achievable via random effects in a Bayesian hierarchical model, but severe computational bottlenecks arise when spatial dependence is encoded as a latent Gaussian process (GP) in the increasingly common large scale data settings on which we focus. The scenario worsens in non-Gaussian models because the reduced analytical tractability leads to additional hurdles to computational efficiency. We introduce methodologies for efficiently computing multivariate Bayesian models of spatially referenced non-Gaussian data.</description></item><item><title>Recent Experiences Conducting Trials using Bayesian Response Adaptive Randomization</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220223/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 14:57:14 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220223/</guid><description>I will discuss my experiences coordinating two recent clinical trials in out-of-hospital cardiac arrest that used Bayesian response adaptive randomization designs, and present some methodological innovations to improve implementation and understand the potential benefit these designs offer. I will discuss the ACCESS trial (Clinicaltrials.gov ID: NCT03119571), which sought to compare the efficacy of two standards or care: direct admission to the cardiac catheter laboratory versus the ICU; and the ARREST trial (NCT03880565), which sought to evaluate the efficacy of in-transit ECMO-facilitated resuscitation versus standard Advanced Cardiac Life Support (ACLS) resuscitation.</description></item><item><title>A Bayesian predictive platform design for proof of concept and dose finding using early and late endpoints</title><link>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220209/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 14:55:53 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://jhublast.github.io/events/20220209/</guid><description>Evaluating long-term benefits of potential new treatments for chronic diseases can be very time-consuming and costly. We propose a Bayesian predictive platform design that provides a unified framework for evaluating multiple investigational agents in a multistage, randomized controlled trial. The design expedites the drug evaluation process and reduces development costs by including dose finding, futility and superiority monitoring, and enrichment, while avoiding over-allocating patients to a shared placebo or active control arm.</description></item></channel></rss>